Project Sinai today's דף daf is סמך טת. samech tes. We pick
up in the middle of סמך טת samech tes עמוד ב amud
bet and we get into a nice little digression which brings us
to a very famous debate. In the משנה mishna רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says you don't do things that are preparatory to- excuse me,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you're allowed to do דרבננס d'rabanans that
you could have done prior but you're allowed to even violate them
now in order to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua disagrees. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua brings as proof
that you can't do certain דרבננס d'rabanans on יום טוב Yom Tov
that you could have done from beforehand like you can't chop firewood
to make the fire even if you're doing it for cooking on
יום טוב Yom Tov to which רבי יהושע- Rabbi Yehoshua רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer responds, that's only a רשות, reshus, קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
is a מצוה, mitzvah, which interestingly has רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying
that having good food on יום טוב Yom Tov is a רשות.
reshus. The גמרא Gemara says this actually connects to another debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua where רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says every יום טוב Yom Tov has to have an
element of לכם, lachem, has to have an element of physical pleasure
of the עונג יום טוב oneg Yom Tov as we call it,
שמחת יום טוב simchas Yom Tov but in the physical thing, and
therefore it's always a מצוה mitzvah and it's relevant to bring that
as evidence for what you can and can't do for קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has no, if you want
you could devote the entire יום טוב Yom Tov to להשם, l'Hashem,
to spiritual שמחה, simcha, and therefore making nice food is not necessarily
a מצוה. mitzvah.
So much for 14 meals in the סוכה. sukkah.
Yeah, that is an interesting issue comparing that to other positions of
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So let's take a look, let's pick that
up quickly from the two dots because we rushed through it a
little bit. So it starts with the word, there's a word א,
aleph, פ, peh, מ mem סימן siman in parentheses about a third
from the bottom of the page. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
I'm sorry no, we'll start a little bit higher, two dots. So
yeah, we'll start two dots, we'll start a third from the top
of the page but we'll do that quickly, but we just worth
rereading that. אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar ומאי פשיטא דרבי יהושע
לטעמיה, umai pshita d'Rabbi Yehoshua l'taimei, רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua opinion that
you can bring a ראיה raaya an evidence from preparing food for
יום טוב Yom Tov to קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is going according
to his reasoning דאמר שמחת יום טוב נמי מצוה d'amar simchas Yom
Tov nami mitzvah that physical pleasure of יום טוב, Yom Tov, שמחת
יום טוב simchas Yom Tov is a מצוה mitzvah and therefore preparing
food for that is comparable to things you do for a קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא baraita רבי
אליעזר אומר אין לו לאדם ביום טוב אלא או אוכל ושותה או
יושב ושונה. Rabbi Eliezer omer ein lo l'adam b'Yom Tov ela o
ochel v'shoteh o yoshev v'shoneh. You have to do one or the
other, it's almost like you're not even allowed to do some type
of a hybrid. You have to dedicate your experience of יום טוב
Yom Tov to a purely spiritual experience or to a purely
physical pleasure אוכל ושותה. ochel v'shoteh. רבי
יהושע אומר חלקהו.
Rabbi Yehoshua
omer chelkeihu. No, you should mix it, חציו לאכילה ולשתיה וחציו לבית
המדרש, chetzyo l'achila v'lishtiya v'chetzyo l'veit hamidrash, half for eating and drinking,
half for the בית המדרש. beit hamidrash. Could be you know an
interesting debate about life and how we achieve certain types of balances
or specialize or focus on particularly one thing. It's missing תפילה. t'filla.
Yeah, good point, the rabbis- for the rabbis the primary religious experience
is learning, is not תפילה, t'filla, but it's an excellent point that
that's absent. It's also worth mentioning you know connected to Rivka's point
about תפילה, t'filla, I was thinking that part of it could connect
to- well let's see where the גמרא Gemara gets it from and
then I'll say something about that. ואמר רבי יוחנן בשם מקרא אחד
דרשו, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan b'shem mikra echad darshu, they both learned it
from one verse. כתוב אחד אומר katuv echad omer one verse says
עצרת להשם אלקיך, Atzeret l'Hashem Elokecha, an עצרת Atzeret a holding back
for השם Hashem your God, וכתוב אחד עצרת תהיה
לכם, v'katuv echad Atzeret tihyeh lachem, for you. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
סבר savar so it once God, once you. או כלו להשם או
כלו לכם, o kulo l'Hashem o kulo lachem, you get to choose
one or the other, presumably again he wouldn't approve of some hybrid.
If you're going to do one, you do it to the to
the to the most extreme degree, all or nothing. רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua סבר חלקהו. savar chelkeihu. No, it has both components, חציו להשם
וחציו לכם, chetzyo l'Hashem v'chetzyo lachem,
half for you and half for God, or half for God half
for you. I would say it's interesting you know because the emphasis
of the תורה Torah very often about the שמחת יום טוב simchas
Yom Tov and about coming to ירושלים Yerushalayim and other things like
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni etc. is that you are שמח לפני השם
sameach lifnei Hashem and it and it sort of incorporates both elements,
you have this physical pleasure but you do it in the presence
of God, in the presence of the מקדש Mikdash and even in
the presence- the גמרא Gemara says אין שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים, ein
simcha ela b'vasar shelamim, by
not just meat but the meat of a שלמים. shelamim. So it's
the physical pleasure and the enjoyment of the bringing of the sacrifice
and somehow connecting that physical שמחה simcha with the שמחה simcha of
being in the presence of God and one is sort of being
you know a manifestation of the other. But here we live the
post-מקדש Mikdash reality so there's some type of a choice that is
being has to now be made between something which at one stage
was much more a an incorporated experience. Now the גמרא Gemara continues,
אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar says Rabbi Elazar, not רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the אמורא, amora, הכל מודים בעצרת
דבעינן נמי לכם. hakol modim b'atzeret d'ba'inan nami lachem. Everybody agrees when
it comes to שבועות Shavuot interestingly, we learn it from עצרת להשם
אלקיך Atzeret l'Hashem Elokecha but that עצרת atzeret is in the פסוקים
psukim is שמיני עצרת. Shmini Atzeret. עצרת Atzeret in the language of
חזל Chazal is שבועות. Shavuot. Everybody agrees that by שבועות Shavuot בעינן
נמי לכם ba'inan nami lachem you need an element, not all לכם,
lachem, but even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that's like
an
absolute Now that’s a little ironic, because you would have thought the
day the תורה Torah was given you would say everybody agrees בעינן
נמי לה', be’inan nami l’Hashem, right? You need to somehow express, especially
as Ribstow pointed out, the emphasis of לה' l’Hashem is not תפילה,
tefilla, but learning תורה. Torah. So you’d say everybody thinks בעינן נמי
לה'. be’inan nami l’Hashem. So רש"י Rashi says the reason he’s making
this claim is because it’s such a day of joy that it
has to, you know, you have to express it in like, you
know, real pleasure of
אכילה ושתיה, achila ushtiya, the joy of the תורה. Torah. Again, it’s
still ironic. I would have suggested and maybe this is just a
דרוש, drush, but I would have suggested a different point, which
is on all the other days of the year you can give,
you know, demonstrate your way of religious expression in purely spiritual pursuits,
and that’s fine. But on יום שניתנה בו תורה, Yom shenitna bo
Torah, you know, the emphasis is this is more like a שבועות
Shavuos תורה Torah tell. But the emphasis is that that’s the day
the תורה Torah was given, meaning it was given to us as
human beings, you know, the famous מדרש Midrash where the מלאכים malachim
say we don’t want it to go down to the earth, and
God says to משה Moshe give an answer, and משה Moshe says,
you know, do you have parents? How are you supposed to כיבוד
אב ואם? kibbud av va’em? Do you have
desire? How does לא תרצח lo tirtzach apply to you? לא תנאף
lo tinaf apply to you? So on the day the תורה Torah
was given, if we were to only learn תורה, Torah, then we
would almost make, you know, if you were, the Christian error
of sort of of thinking that religious experience, like the day of
the תורה, Torah, תורה Torah remains up in heaven and our religious
experience is to put ourselves, you know, monastically in a cave and
just not, you know, have it completely as a religious experience sealed
off from translating it to how we live in this world. So
on other days of the year we’re not afraid of that mixed
message because other days of the year are not, you know, are
not hyper-focused on the תורה. Torah. But a day that’s totally focused
on the תורה, Torah, we have to make sure that we demonstrate
that the idea of the תורה Torah being given to us is
to be translated into how we live our lives, you know, in
the physical experience of this world, and that actually you can take
something like a מצוה mitzvah and a מצוה mitzvah can express itself
through אכילה ושתיה. achila ushtiya. A מצוה mitzvah doesn’t just have to
express itself through closing yourself off from the physical and, you know,
engaging in purely spiritual pursuits.
Even the some of the תלמידי talmidei warriors wasn't going to be
enough food.
Well, that they wouldn't have enough. You know, but it’s even a
little thing that’s nice that makes it special. Anyway, so that’s my,
that’s my little שבועות Shavuot דבר תורה. dvar Torah. What?
You say it over in שול. shul. Yeah.
I was going to say we’ll have the long version at 3:30
AM at שבועות. Shavuot. If you see these things, then we don’t
necessarily have to be worried about that because
we’re more focused on ביכורים Bikkurim or whatever it is. Well, that’s
true. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
הכל מודים בשבת. hakol modim beShabbat. Now, for a more regular thing
that applies there for, you know, one or two days a year,
but for a more regular point, everybody also agrees on שבת Shabbat
דבעינן נמי לכם, debe’inan nami lachem, you need
לכם. lachem. מאי טעמא Mai ta’ama why? וקראת לשבת עונג, vekarata l’Shabbat
Oneg, you should call שבת Shabbat עונג, Oneg, which is a day
of pleasure. And you know, there’s a difference between עונג Oneg and
שמחה. simcha. שמחה Simcha is joy. A lot of things can bring
people joy. Not everybody brings joy by a good meal. For some
people joy is from a good meal. You know, everybody might appreciate
a good meal, or they might enjoy a good meal, but it
doesn’t necessarily mean that a good meal brings joy. Joy can come
through a lot of other things.
A good nap. Joy could come from a wonderful conversation with friends.
Joy could come from an amazing, you know, an amazing place. So
joy, which is this much greater sense of like elevation and completion,
you know, that can be experienced differently and therefore for some people
it could be כולו לה' kulo l’Hashem and that could bring שמחה.
simcha. But שבת, Shabbat, שמחה simcha is an idea that’s emphasized on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. שבת Shabbat is, and the idea that is
emphasized is not שמחה simcha on שבת Shabbat but עונג, Oneg, physical
pleasure. וקראת לשבת עונג. Vekarata l’Shabbat Oneg. And therefore everybody agrees that
דבעינן נמי לכם. debe’inan nami lachem.
Right. So there’s the idea of כבוד שבת, kavod Shabbat, but there’s
an idea of עונג שבת. Oneg Shabbat. The whole idea of שלוש
סעודות, shalosh seudot, you know, all of the a lot of specific
הלכות halachot by שבת Shabbat about how you make the meal because
specifically עונג Oneg is a unique שבת Shabbat concept. Now, you could
then ask, okay, that’s very nice, you’ve described those words, but why?
Why is עונג Oneg something to emphasize by שבת? Shabbat? You know,
and again I think you could make a similar point to the
one I made about שבועות, Shavuot, that by שבת Shabbat you are
not preparing food, right? And you by שבת Shabbat you are, you
therefore it’s a, it’s easier not,
you know, it’d be easier not to have to worry about making
שבת Shabbat physically enjoyable. But also you could imagine that if it’s
a day of cessation, it’s also supposed to be a day that’s
supposed to be like
purely spiritual.
The רמב"ם Rambam says, because we’re coming up to ימים נוראים Yamim
Noraim here, רמב"ם Rambam says why do we fast, implicit in the
רמב"ם Rambam is why we fast on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is
not so much the idea of we somehow afflict ourselves as a
way of doing תשובה, teshuva, but the רמב"ם Rambam ties it into
the idea that יום כיפור Yom Kippur is שבת שבתון. Shabbat Shabbaton.
a full שבת. Shabbat. What does that mean? שבת ממלאכה, Shabbat mimlacha,
שבת מאכילה ושתיה. Shabbat mei'achila v'shtiya. Like it's a full cessation of
our physical embodiedness, our physical activities, whether it's engagement in the world,
or whether it's eating and drinking, we're supposed to make it a
purely spiritual day and rest from all those parts that are our
physical engagement with the world. So that's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that's
a שבת שבתון. Shabbat Shabbaton. But the other שבתות, Shabbats, again, you
know, you could actually or you need to make sure that there's
the עונג Oneg as well, and once it's either so as I
said before you don't go overboard and too much drive into this
idea that the ideal Jewish religious ideal is to write off the
physical world, but you could also say so you don't associate with,
you know, my son, thank God not so much now, but you
know, used to have a really really hard time that שבת Shabbat
was the least enjoyable day and he looked and he dreaded שבת
Shabbat because what can't you do what can't you do on שבת?
Shabbat? Can't do your computer games, exactly. So if the idea of
a day that is to give you rest from the whole world
means a day that it does not have the type of physical
enjoyment that you have during the week, right, then that becomes then
it becomes associate with that sense of you know deprivation, exactly. And
as opposed to associate with that sense of separating from the world
and devoting a special, you know, day to God as some sense
of a source of pleasure and enjoyment. So by שבת Shabbat is
a space specifically we have to make sure that we have the
לכם lachem and we have עונג Oneg and we even emphasize it
more than we would during a normal day of the week.
It's interesting because it's not just the לכם, lachem, you know, mean
not having any fire, you know who'd heat up food, you know,
in the dark.
That's true too. That's true too. And there's definitely some, you know,
I believe it was the צדוקים Tzedukim that said, or maybe it
was the כת המדבר Kat haMidbar that basically said that you're not
allowed to have sex on שבת. Shabbat. It was the כת המדבר.
Kat haMidbar. It was the כת המדבר, Kat haMidbar, might have also
been because like procreative, what's more creative than having sex, you know,
and דווקא davka we know that that's specifically directed, you know, that
husband and wife are supposed to have sex. So you could be
right as well that there's some of that, you know, some of
that going on here in as well. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. אמר רב יוסף הכל מודין בפורים דבעינן נמי לכם.
Amar Rav Yosef, hakol modin b'Purim d'ba'inan nami lachem. Oh,
that we don't need him to tell us. Everybody agrees that פורים
Purim is a day of physical pleasure. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
But where would you thought the other way, in other words?
I don't know because it's not really, you're right, it's not like
it's something that says, you know once we're talking about all the
ימים טובים, Yomim Tovim, right, it's not like שבת Shabbat has שמחה,
simcha, but anyway, מאי טעמא דקרא, mai ta'ama d'kara, it says ימי
משתה ושמחה כתיב ביה. yemei mishteh v'simcha ketiv beh. So it's not
the שמחה simcha we're דרשנינג darshening here, it's the ימי משתה, yemei
mishteh, okay, of drinking, which obviously reflects the, you know, the story
of פורים. Purim. מר בריה דרבינא כולי שתא הוה יתיב בתעניתא. Mar
brei d'Ravina kulei shata hava yativ b'ta'anita. מר Mar the son of
רבינא, Ravina, the entire year he would sit in a תענית, ta'anit,
presumably a day תענית ta'anit and eat at night. So his entire
year would be, it would be a year of Ramadan every year
for him. לבר מעצרתא ופוריא ומעלי יומא דכיפורי, levar mei'Atzarta u'Puraya u'ma'alei
Yoma d'Kippuri,
with the exception of שבועות, Shavuot, פורים, Purim, and ערב יום כיפור.
Erev Yom Kippur. So presumably also שבת. Shabbat. You don't sit in
a תענית ta'anit on שבת. Shabbat. Presumably not on יום טוב Yom
Tov either. Well, I don't know, it sounds like everything. So presumably
it would be on יום
טוב Yom Tov and שבת? Shabbat? According to this גמרא, Gemara, it
seems like, according to this גמרא Gemara it
seems
like he rejected the idea of, look, we do know there is
an idea of having a תענית חלום ta'anit chalom on שבת, Shabbat,
you know. I don't know, you're right, I was, it does sound
like I'm trying to be, I'm trying to make it a little
tame, tame the גמרא Gemara down, but it does sound like every,
the entire year, right, even on יום טוב, Yom Tov, only שבועות,
Shavuot, it would seem like even on שבת. Shabbat. ערב
פסח? Erev Pesach? What? No, not ערב, Erev, it doesn't say that.
It's a good point.
Makes this bar really hard. עצרתא יום שניתנה בו תורה. Atzarta, yom
she'nitna bo Torah. פוריא ימי משתה ושמחה כתיב. Puraya, yemei mishteh v'simcha
ketiv. So two we've already mentioned. Somehow he did not pay attention
to the שבת Shabbat one, if we're reading it correctly. ומעלי יומא
דכיפורי, u'ma'alei Yoma d'Kippuri, and ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, דתניא
חייא בר רב מדפתי d'tanya Chiya bar Rav mi-Diftei as he taught,
ועניתם את נפשותיכם בתשעה לחודש, v'innitem et nafshoteichem b'tish'a lachodesh, you should
afflict your soul on the ninth. So one דרשה drasha means why
does it say the ninth, why doesn't it just refer to the,
I mean it's the ninth at night, which means the tenth, but
just say the tenth. So one דרשה drasha is you have to
start fasting a little into the tenth, into the ninth, before the
tenth.
But here the גמרא Gemara has another דרשה. drasha. וכי בתשעה מתענה
ולא בעשירי מתענה? v'chi b'tish'a mitaneh v'lo b'asiri mitaneh? Do we fast
on the ninth? Do we not fast on the
tenth? אלא לומר לך כל האוכל ושותה בתשעה בו, ela lomar lach,
kol ha'ochel v'shoteh b'tish'a bo, if you eat and drink on the
ninth, מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו התענה תשיעי ועשירי, ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu
hitaneh tish'a v'asiri, then it's like, hopefully you also fasted on the
tenth, but okay, if you eat and drink on the ninth, then
it counts like you fasted both the ninth and the tenth. I
never understood that. Yeah, so it's hard to understand what is the
point of this. Some ראשונים Rishonim say that the point, I mean,
I'll give you three basic explanations that are given or, one is
since you can't have שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov and כבוד
יום טוב kavod Yom Tov on whatever שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom
Tov on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, we sort of displace it to
ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, which is why people make a
nice, they set their table and do a nice thing in order
to sort of, you know, have that experience on
ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom Kippur. The other idea is that, which
again, maybe goes against simple פשט *Peshat* of the פסוקים psukim, *Pesukim*,
maybe like the רמב"ם *Rambam* I said before, that the idea of
fasting is not supposed to make you suffer. Some people would think
otherwise. So, whatever it's supposed to do, right, let's say like the
רמב"ם *Rambam*, it's supposed to separate you from the physical for one
day, but it's not about suffering. So, you're supposed to דוקא davka
*davka* eat on the ninth in order so that you could fast
without it being too much of a hardship. And then, you know,
you're doing the fasting maybe for the right reason, not as some
sort of self-flagellation type of an experience. Again, not sure that's exactly
the פשט *Peshat*. What I would suggest is also the idea that,
somewhat like I said before by the issue of שבועות *Shavuot*, that,
you know, it's easy to see that, you know, to sort of
connect a sense of religious actions, serving God, by not eating. It's,
in a way, it's even harder to see how we're serving God
by eating. So, and דוקא *davka* on the day where you're going
to be totally about, you know, divorcing yourself from the world, fasting,
and again, sort of creating that as some type of an ideal
religious experience, we have to also the day before see that we,
you know, that equally important is how we serve God when we're
actually living in this world and how we make our אכילה ושתיה
*achila ushtiya* on ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur* also into an
act of a מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah*. I am always remembered of a
story about I was once had the זכות *zechut* to know a
certain rabbi who was actually a תלמיד *talmid* of the, of the
חפץ חיים *Chofetz Chaim*, and he, no, yeah, and he was part
of the when the מיר ישיבה *Mir Yeshiva* moved to Shanghai. And
I asked him, is it really true that people fasted two days
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* because they didn't know, you know, there was
a debate where the international date line was? So he said, he
said, no, only like some יחידי סגולה *yechidei segula*. Most people just
had a פסק *psak* in which day was יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*.
But anyway, but then he told me, you know, that it came
to a time on
ערב יום כיפור *Erev
Yom Kippur*, well anyway, it came to a time where he wasn't
able to fast on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* because of his health.
And, you know, this was like, it was a tragedy for him
because he had his entire life, and he was ninety-something years old,
fasted on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, that he would actually have to
eat on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. You know, how is he going
to do this? So he said, said,
doctor said to me, he said, he said the same way you
served God all these years by fasting on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*,
now you're going to serve God by eating on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. So which I always just so powerful, you know. So, and
it's a challenge, you know, it's a real challenge to be able
to see it in that way, especially at this time of year.
So I don't know if there was a פרום *frum* doctor or
he had sensitivity.
Yeah, that's a good question. Right.
Well, I think the רב *Rav* says about this in the nineties,
is to make a demonstrative distinction between the ninth and the tenth.
Uh-huh, sort of like why we don't blow שופר Shofar *shofar* on
ערב ראש השנה *Erev Rosh Hashanah*.
I mean, I think he also says you're supposed to sit down
for אשרי *Ashrei* at מנחה *Mincha* so that when you stand up,
you're מבדיל *mavdil*, you make a distinction. So I think he uses
the same reason.
Oh, okay, that's very nice.
And then, you know, it's sort of the רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* way
that
by עצרת *Atzeret* we're demonstrating that we're happy that נוח *noach*, that
we had our, you know, they have תורה Torah. *Torah*, so the
other of the ninth was that you're happy to show that you
have רישומא דכפרה *rishuma de'chapara*.
Right, I mean, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, so that's a variation
of the idea of sort of displacing the שמחת יום טוב simchat
Yom Tov. *Simchat Yom Tov*, right, that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
לא lo. היו ימים טובים בישראל כחמישה עשר באב וכיום הכיפורים *lo
hayu yamim tovim b'Yisrael k'chamisha asar b'Av u'k'Yom HaKippurim*, יום שניתנה בו
*yom shenitna bo*, you know, יום הכיפורים *Yom Kippur* is a day
of סליחה ומחילה וכפרה *slicha u'mechila u'chapara*. So how do you express
that שמחה simcha *simcha*? You can't have it on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, so you have it on ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur*.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this: רב יוסף
ביומא דעצרתא *Rav Yosef b'yoma d'atzereta*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* on שבועות
*Shavuot*, אמר Amar... עבדי לי עגלא תלתא *amar avdi li egla tlata*,
make for me a third calf. There's a question always what that
means. Does it mean a third born? Or does it mean a
three-year-old? But sometimes this was a, this was some type of a
very special dish, a very special calf that was, you know, when
you really wanted to indulge and enjoy, have a real, you know,
a very pleasurable type of a, of a meal,
it would use, it would be this עגלא תלתא *egla tlata*. אמר
*Amar*, and here's how he expressed it, why this is יום שניתנה
בו תורה Torah *yom shenitna bo Torah*, but let's see how he
expressed this. אי לאו האי יומא דקא גרים *ei lav
hai yoma d'ka garim*, were it not for this day that had
caused, or caused what, well, you know, me being Jewish, me to
be, you know, sort of learned תורה Torah *Torah* is what he's
going to mean. If it were not for the importance of this
day and everything that it brought about, כמה יוסף איכא בשוקא *kama
Yosef ika b'shuka*, there'd be a lot of Josephs out in the
marketplace. He's רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. I'd just be a normal Joe,
you know, if it weren't for, if it weren't for יום שניתנה
בו תורה Torah *yom shenitna bo Torah*. It's the יום שניתנה בו
תורה Torah *yom shenitna bo Torah* that, it's not like I'm better
than, well, sort of, but not, but the point is is that
I have, you know, it gives me my religious purpose in life.
It makes everything different for me. And therefore it's the day where
I have particular שמחה.
And now we're going to see an interesting sort of follow-up to
that. רב ששת Rav Sheshet כל תלתין יומין מהדר ליה לתלמודיה. kol
taltin yomin mahader lei letalmudei. Every רב ששת Rav Sheshet every thirty
days he would, he would חזר chazer all of his learning. Maybe
he would חזר ש״ס chazer Shas every thirty days. And and you
think the דף יומי Daf Yomi is tough. Okay. ותלי וקאי בעיברא
דדשא vtali vkai beivra dedasha
and then he would go and like, you know, hang out by
the, by the, over by the, by the bridge, by you know,
by the river bank. ואמר vamar and he'd say חדאי נפשאי חדאי
נפשאי. chadai nafshai chadai nafshai. Oh
my soul is so happy, my soul rejoices. לך קראי לך תנאי.
lach karai lach tanai. For you my soul have I learned, for
you have I, you know, פסוקים, תורה. Torah, For you have I
learned, you know, משנה, Mishna, have I learned, you know, the the
rabbinic material. So basically, what what this is, I get so much
pleasure from his learning. Now, of course, you know, it's interesting. Here
it's the שמחה from the learning. It's not translating in, and therefore
I have to have a very nice meal, which was part of
the discussion before. But it is a comparable to the earlier story
about how these you know great תורה Torah sages, you know, got
so much pleasure from their, from what it meant for them to
be doing a life of תורה Torah. and how much pleasure that
gave them and how much joy that gave them. איני? ini? Says
the גמרא. Gemara Is that really true? That he feels like like
his תורה Torah learning is something he personally takes pleasure in. והאמר
רב אלעזר, veha'amar Rav Elazar, and did did רב אלעזר Rav Elazar
say אלמלא תורה לא נתקיימו שמים וארץ? ilmalei Torah lo nitkaymu shamayim
va'aretz? Were
it not for תורה Torah the heavens and earth would not be
established. שנאמר, shenemar, if not, אם לא בריתי, im lo briti, were
it not for my covenant, יומם ולילה, yomam valaila, day and night,
meaning the תורה, Torah, חוקות שמים וארץ לא שמתי. chukot shamayim va'aretz
lo shamti. The the very principles, you know, the of nature, of
heaven and earth I would not have created. So meaning, the תורה
Torah. keeps the world going. You shouldn't sort of be experiencing this
as, oh I so much love תורה. Torah It's not about you,
it's about, you know, God, it's about the world. So what is
this sort of personal sense of pleasure that you're taking? So the
גמרא Gemara, says, you know what? That might be true, but מעיקרא
כי עביד איניש אדעתא דנפשיה קעביד. meikara ki avid inish ada'ata denafshei
ka'avid. It could be people's תורה keeps the world going, but what
gets people initially to throw themselves into it is, you know, is
their own personal investment. That's my paraphrase of the גמרא. Gemara When
people go ahead and do it, they do it on their, you
know, based on their on their own mind, you know? People are
motivated based on what's personally speaking to them. And it really speaks
to, you know, this idea of like joy and we just had
a, a little retreat the other day and I was sharing with
the students, you know, that I think what first put me on
a path of real, you know, investing in the learning of תורה
was a רבי Rebbe I had in high school who just his
whole approach to it was one of like fun and one of
joy. And that's very, you know, and that, that really creates a
profound sense of love, you know? And it gives me pleasure and
it gives me joy. Like the פסוק pasuk says תורה שעשוע. Torah
sha'ashua. So, you know, obviously don't think that that's all it is.
It's not just like, oh I could read a good book, I
could learn תורה, they both give me joy. Obviously you understand that
חוקות שמים וארץ לא שמתי. chukot shamayim va'aretz lo shamti. There's this
much bigger, you know, obviously the great religious majesty and importance of
the learning of תורה. But the investment, the initial investment comes because
of a sense of pleasure and joy and an investment and and
that personal investment. And that, so you have that in these two
stories, and you have that in translating into really giving like, you
know, expression of the
בעינא נמי לכם, beina nami lachem, of having, you know, of really
showing that joy. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. So after that
beautiful passage, back to the real joy of learning תורה which is
the, which is the normal discussions in the גמרא, Gemara I guess
it depends. Okay, anyway. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, ולמאי דקאמר
רבי אליעזר נמי יום טוב רשות. ulemai dekamar Rabi Eliezer nami Yom
Tov reshut. So back to business. So that which רבי אליעזר Rabi
Eliezer says that יום טוב Yom Tov is a רשות, reshut, right?
Because he said you don't, it's not necessarily, you can't bring proof
from שמחת יום טוב. simchat Yom Tov, It's not necessarily a מצוה.
mitzvah You could devote the whole יום טוב Yom Tov to learn
it. So according to him, אית ליה פירכא. it lei pircha. You
could also contradict his position that he says that you can't do,
you can't, he allows you to do דרבננס Derabanans and feels that
you can't bring a proof from the prohibition regarding יום טוב. Yom
Tov. You could even you can challenge that. ומה יום טוב שהותרה
בו מלאכה של רשות לא הותרה שבות עמו. umah Yom Tov shehutra
bo melacha shel reshut lo hutra shevut imo. Fine, you think cooking
on יום טוב Yom Tov is a רשות. reshut. So still, use
that as evidence. On יום טוב Yom Tov you're allowed to cook
which is a רשות, reshut, it's not a מצוה mitzvah for you,
שמחת יום טוב, simchat Yom Tov. or or the physical שמחת יום
טוב. Yom Tov? And nevertheless, you're not allowed to do דרבננס. Derabanans.
You can do cooking but you can't go ahead and do even
דרבננס Derabanans that you could have done the day before. שבת שלא
הותרה בה מלאכה של מצוה. Shabbat shelo hutra ba melacha shel mitzvah.
When it comes to a פסח Pesach that falls out on שבת,
Shabbat, that you're only not allowed to do רשות, reshut, you're only
allowed to do מצוה mitzvah, like the מצות קרבן פסח. mitzvat Korban
Pesach. So, אינו דין שלא
תתיר שבות עמו? eino din shelo tatir shevut imo? So by שבת
Shabbat which is more restrictive, you're not allowed to do רשות reshut
like cooking, you can only do קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So if
it's more restrictive, how much more so should you not be able
to do the דרבננס Derabanans that accompany that that מצוה, mitzvah, the
same way you can't do the דרבננס Derabanans that accompany cooking on
יום טוב? Yom Tov רבי אליעזר, Rabi Eliezer, now back to the
סמיכה smicha etc.
Trying to prove against רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer who allowed you to
do דרבננס drabbanans for קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, even דרבננס drabbanans you
could have done the day before, like bringing the קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, but admits that you cannot do דרבננס drabbanans you could have
done the day before on יום טוב Yom Tov for cooking. So
the argument is true, פסח Pesach there's more license because it's a
מצוה, mitzvah, but if but but שבת Shabbos
is more restrictive, and if שבת Shabbos is more restrictive and you
can only do the מצוה, mitzvah. then certainly you should be more
restrictive and not allow you do these דרבננס. drabbanans. רבי אליעזר, Rebbi
Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer would still say back, I'm sorry, it's
true שבת Shabbos is more restrictive, but at least now we're talking
about doing things for the sake of a מצוה. mitzvah שבות דמצוה
עדיף ליה. Shvus d'mitzvah adif lei. The fact that דרבננס drabbanans are
allowing you to do the מצוה mitzvah of קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
that would override even שבת. Shabbos. So so it is true that
יום טוב Yom Tov is generally less restrictive, but what's sort of
overriding is also less powerful. And when you're doing a דרבנן drabbanan
for the sake of doing the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, that you're
going to be allowed to do according to רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer.
שחיטת קרבן פסח?
Shechitas
Korban Pesach?
Yeah, and and מילה, milah, things that would anyway override שבת. Shabbos.
We haven't mentioned מילה milah yet, but yes. So תניא, tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rebbi Eliezer, ומה
אם דוחה מכשירי מצוה שלאחר שחיטה את השבת, uma im docha machshirei
mitzvah she-le'achar shechita es ha-Shabbos,
he's going to prove you're allowed to do דרבננס drabbanans that will
enable you to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even if you
could have done them beforehand. What's the story that I allow you
to do מכשירי מצוה? machshirei mitzvah? Now מכשיר machshir usually means something
that prepares and enables, but in this context it also means things
that are sort of
appendant to, associated with the מצוה mitzvah but not the מצוה mitzvah
itself. You can do those things even after the שחיטה shechita and
they will override שבת. Shabbos. So what's he referring to? So according
to תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos has a simpler read than רש"י, he
says it's referring to burning the fats, right? You could wait till
after יום טוב Yom Tov to after שבת Shabbos to burn the
fats of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
you brought on שבת. Shabbos. It could be brought that night when
it's only a יום טוב issue, but no, you do it on
שבת. Shabbos. So it's comparable. You're telling me, says רבי אליעזר, Rebbi
Eliezer, you could have brought the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you could
have carried it, you know, ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, you could have
cut off this מום mum ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, so you're not
going to allow this guy to do it on שבת. Shabbos. You
know what? The fats you could burn on מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbos,
and even so we let you burn it on שבת. Shabbos. So
if that's true, מה מכשירי מצוה שלאחר שחיטה דוחה את השבת, mah
machshirei mitzvah she-le'achar shechita docha es ha-Shabbos, if the fats that can
burn that come after שחיטה shechita you can do on שבת, Shabbos,
even though you could have waited and done it מוצאי שבת, motzei
Shabbos, דסב
ליה מצוה, desab lei mitzvah, then your מצוה's mitzvah already done. You
don't need to burn the fats to enable you to bring the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, even when it's done, you're allowed to do
that on שבת. Shabbos. וכי תמיד עצמו?
v'chi tamid atzmo?
Right, well, right, לא ידחו מכשירי מצוה שלפני שחיטה את השבת? lo
yidchu machshirei mitzvah she-lifnei shechita es ha-Shabbos? Then certainly the things that
prepare before the שחיטה shechita that allow you to bring the קרבן
פסח, Korban Pesach, like cutting off the מום mum or carrying it,
how much more so should that override? אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar
lo Rebbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said back to him,
דמה לי d'mah li or דמה היא, d'mah hee, what type of
comparison is that? אם דחו מכשירי מצוה שלאחר שחיטה את השבת, im
dachu machshirei mitzvah she-le'achar shechita es ha-Shabbos, why do the things after
שחיטה shechita override שבת Shabbos like burning the fats even though you
could wait till the night? שהרי דחתה שחיטה את השבת, sheharei dachsa
shechita es ha-Shabbos, the שבת Shabbos has already been overridden, and then
you're like just carrying on the momentum, or you're on the coat-tails.
Right? So once the פסח, Pesach, the act of פסח Pesach has
overridden שבת, Shabbos, now everything else is just wrapping it up, but
it's part of that היתר hetter of bringing the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach which you already began and you already did, it already overrode.
תאמר ידחו מכשירי מצוה שלפני שחיטה את השבת? tomar yidchu machshirei mitzvah
she-lifnei shechita es ha-Shabbos? Will you say the things that come before
the שחיטה shechita that are going to enable the פסח Pesach to
be brought will override? שלא דחתה שחיטה את השבת, shelo dachsa shechita
es ha-Shabbos, you have not yet had the פסח Pesach overriding. Now
it's a little hard to understand that because you know the argument
is still, I don't get it, the point is to bring the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, this is going to allow you to bring
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Isn't it more important to allow you
to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach than it is to just
sort of mop-up type of stuff, you know, which is sort of
what what is רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer argument? But it seems the
difference here is, you know, how much do we think about it
as the מצוה Mitzvah, of קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Your personal Michael,
נבך, Nebach, we want you to bring the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
that could override שבת, Shabbos, or is it no, the עבודת הקרבן
avodas ha-korban overrides שבת? Shabbos? Right? So if you think about it
as your obligation and your need for you to bring the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach overrides, so certainly we should override the things that
if we do after the bringing of it, we should certainly do
the things that are going to enable you to bring it. But
if we think about it that the קרבן korban overrides, that's what
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says. So once you're bringing the קרבן, korban,
everything related to the הקרבה hakrava of the קרבן korban overrides, but
not enabling you to bring the קרבן, korban, that's not what overrides,
it's the הקרבה hakrava of the קרבן korban that overrides, and you
can't make that comparison. So that's רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva response to
רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. You know, there is definitely something very attractive
about רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer position. All right, we don't פסקן pasken
him. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara gets into דבר אחר, davar acher,
here's another counter argument, שמא ימצא זבח פסול ונמצא מחלל שבת למפרע.
shema yimatzei zevach pasul v'nimtza mechallel Shabbos l'mafrei'a.
I'm not going to let you violate שבת Shabbos with דרבננס drabbanans
you could have done beforehand because let's say you do a bad
שחיטה shechita and the... it's פסול *pasul*. Everything you would have done
would not have had the justification of overriding שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* and
therefore I have to limit the things that come prior although I
can give more license to the thing itself. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does not like that for obvious reasons. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אי הכי שחיטה Shechita. נמי לא נשחוט שמא ימצא זבח פסול
ונמצא מחלל שבת Shabbat? למפרע *Ei hachi shechita nami lo nishchot shema
yimtza zevach pasul venimtza mechaleil Shabbat le'mafrea*. So don't bring the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach. *korban Pesach* to begin with. Don't שחט shacht *shacht*
it. Maybe it'll be פסול *pasul*. Obviously we do things because whatever
license we're given we're given because because and we don't have to
be concerned about that. אלא הא אמר ליה amar lei, ברישא *Ela
ha amar lei be'reisha*. So you're right. This second point is really
what he said first. ופרכיה *U'parcheih*. And he contradicted him. He gave
the obvious response. That's not a proof. Obviously we're not worried about
שמא ימצא פסול *shema yimtza pasul*. והדר אמר ליה amar lei, הא
דמלי ודחיה *Ve'hadar amar lei ha demali vedachyei*. And then right exactly
then don't do anything. Anyway and then he gave back to the
first one. So when it was written down it wrote the stronger
argument first and then threw in the other one even though that
was really a weaker argument. Okay basically I do think one way
of understanding the debate is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer* says
the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* the ability to perform the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*
overrides so things that are getting in the way of the
performance even if they come prior more so if they come prior
they're getting in the way of performance and therefore they should be
overridden. Whereas I think what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* is
saying is no it's the הקרבה *hakrava* of the קרבן korban *korban*
and therefore we can only start talking once you're bringing the קרבן
*korban* and things associated with הקרבה *hakrava*. Not things that are oh
my
god I have to drive to Cincinnati now to pick it up
because I forgot it. That's not the הקרבה *hakrava* of the קרבן
*korban*. I'm sorry if it's getting in your way but that's not
the הקרבה *hakrava* of the קרבן *korban*. Okay השיב רבי עקיבא ואמר
Heishiv Rabbi Akiva v'amar, הזאה Haza'ah תוכיח *Heishiv Rabbi Akiva ve'amar haza'ah
tochiach*. Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* tries to prove it
from הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*. He says look we all agree that הזאה
Haza'ah *haza'ah* of a טמא מת Tamei Mes, *tamei meis* you can't
do the הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah* on the seventh day even though that's
getting in the way of him bringing the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach.
*korban Pesach*. And the הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah* is only דרבנן De'Rabanan *d'rabanan*.
So you see you can't do דרבננס De'Rabanans *d'rabanans* that are getting
in the way if in this role something that could even be
done earlier. It's the seventh day. But even that can't be done
because conceptually there's no
need to do an idea that the day of הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*
is ערב פסח Erev Pesach, *erev Pesach*. The only thing that overrides
is the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban Pesach* because the day of
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban Pesach* is ערב פסח Erev Pesach,
*erev Pesach* that overrides.
That's stronger than a logical argument. Right it becomes first if
we all agree that you don't do הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*. But רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer's* response is who said I agree to
that? I say you can do הזאה Haza'ah. *haza'ah* in order to
enable the guy to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach.
*korban Pesach*. Just in general let's say going to the מקוה Mikvah
*mikveh* טבילה בזמנה מצוה Mitzvah. *tevilah bizmanah mitzvah* whatever it is you're
allowed to do let's say you forgot to do something you could
have done earlier.
Yeah
so that is discussed. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this תניא *tanya*. אמר לו רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Amar lo
Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer* said back to him
עקיבא *Akiva*. So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* said I'll remind you the end
of the give and take. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* said
no I think you can do הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*. So רבי Rebbe,
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said like almost a foolish type of a
thing it wasn't a real argument. He said oh why don't we
say this you can't do you say the same way you can
do שחיטה *shechita* you can do הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*. Let's say the
same way you can't do הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah* you can't do שחיטה
*shechita*. And he said what are you talking about? Obviously you can
do שחיטה *shechita*. It says במועדו *bemo'ado*. So it was a funny
thing that רבי Rebbe, עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said. So let's hear what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer... *Rabbi Eliezer* said back to him. אמר לו
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* said back to him עקיבא בשחיטה השבתני *Akiva bishchita heshivatani*.
You're trying to answer me up by שחיטה *shechita* saying oh let's
say this you can't do הזאה Haza'ah. *haza'ah* you can't do שחיטה
*shechita* right and what you want to say you can't do שחיטה
*shechita* you can't do הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah*. בשחיטה תהא מיתתו *Bishchita tehei
mitato*. The death maybe it was euphemistic your death or the death
of your argument will come through
שחיטה *shechita*. Okay so he was answering him in a mocking back
way. I'm going to שחט *shacht* your argument. Such a silly argument
of course you do שחיטה *shechita*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אמר לו רבי Rebbe, *amar lo rebbi*. So רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
said back to him רבי *rebbi* my master because רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* was רבי
עקיבא'ס *Rabbi Akiva's* רבי *rebbi*. אל תקפחני בשעת הדין *Al tikpacheini bishat
hadin*. Do not
reject me when we're having an argument. Do you really want to
go one to one with me in an
argument? Please don't try to just push me off and reject what
I'm saying in an argument. Why? כך מקובלני ממך *Kach mekublani mimcha*.
Because this is really a tradition I have from you. Yes yes
yes right you can say right הזאה Haza'ah שבות ואינה דוחה Doche,
את השבת
*Haza'ah shevut ve'einah docha et ha'shabbat*.
You have taught me the tradition that הזאה Haza'ah? *haza'ah* is true
it's only rabbinic but you do not override it on שבת Shabbat?
*Shabbat* even to bring the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban Pesach*. This is a tradition that I
have from
you. So that's why I made a foolish argument because I wanted
to make a point. The point I was making was when I
say why don't we say the same way הזאה Haza'ah *haza'ah* doesn't
override שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* שחיטה *shechita* does not override שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*.
That's crazy but what you hear from that is that I'm taking
as an axiomatic principle that הזאה Haza'ah, *haza'ah* does not override שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat*. And I'm saying such a foolish thing 'cause I want
you to hear that I'm taking this as an axiomatic principle 'cause
I know this from you. So don't say that you don't agree
to this idea that הזאה Haza'ah. does not override שבת. Shabbat So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכי מאחר דהוא אגמריה, V'chi
mei'achda d'hu agmrei, so Rabbi Eliezer really taught Rabbi Akiva that הזאה
Haza'ah. does not override שבת? Shabbat, So מאי טעמא קהדר ביה? mai
ta'ama kahadar bei? Why is Rabbi Eliezer backtracking and saying I actually
think הזאה Haza'ah? does override שבת? Shabbat So normally you would say
people can change their minds, but remember let's remember that Rabbi Eliezer
is all about the traditions that he has received. So אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, so עולא Ulla says Rabbi Eliezer כי אגמריה הזאה דתרומה
אגמריה. ki agmrei hazah d'trumah agmrei. No, no, no, actually it was
a little miscommunication. When Rabbi Eliezer said you don't do הזאה Haza'ah
on שבת Shabbat. even for a מצוה, Mitzvah, he didn't mean the
מצוה Mitzvah, of קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach That you would do on
שבת. Shabbat He meant the מצוה Mitzvah of like eating תרומה. Trumah.
You're טמא מת, Tamei Mes, you have to do הזאה Haza'ah, so
you could eat תרומה, Trumah, that's when he said we don't do
it for a
מצוה. ותרומה גופה לא דחי שבת, V'trumah gufa lo dachi Shabbat, 'cause
there's no special היתר, Heter, you know, that allows you to override
שבת Shabbat, for תרומה, Trumah, so you don't override שבת Shabbat to
go to do הזאה Haza'ah to eat תרומה. Trumah. רבי עקיבא נמי
כי אותביה הזאה דתרומה אותביה. Rabbi Akiva nami ki otvei hazah d'trumah
otvei. And when Rabbi Akiva was challenging him, he was challenging him
with הזאה דתרומה. Haza'ah d'Trumah. He says it's true, תרומה Trumah doesn't
override שבת, Shabbat? but it's still a מצוה, eating תרומה. Trumah. And
therefore we don't do הזאה Haza'ah, on שבת Shabbat? even for the
sake of a מצוה, so we shouldn't do it for a פסח.
Pesach. Obviously that's not a great argument because פסח Pesach itself
overrides שבת. Shabbat Anyway, שהיא מצוה והיא משום שבות, shehi mitzvah v'hi
mishum shvut, it has exactly the characters you said, it's a מצוה
and it only has the rabbinic thing getting in the way, and
we still don't do
it. והוא סבר הזאה דפסח קמותיב ליה. V'hu savar hazah d'Pesach kamotvei
leh. And but Rabbi Eliezer thought that when Rabbi Akiva was trying
to prove to him from the הזאה Haza'ah. of the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach, And he said back to him, Akiva, it's not what
I said, for the פסח Pesach you would override שבת Shabbat to
do the הזאה. Haza'ah, So that's the way the גמרא Gemara has
it, they were just completely miscommunicating. Of course, it's hard to understand
what Rabbi Akiva thought he was proving, obviously הזאה Haza'ah, for תרומה
Trumah is very different. So מתיב רבא, Motiv Rava, so רבא Rava
doesn't believe that's the right version. Here's a ברייתא. Baraita. השיב רבי
עקיבא ואמר, Rabbi Akiva responded to Rabbi Eliezer and said, and here's
the ברייתא Baraita which is explicit. הזאת טמא מת תוכיח, Hazat tmei
mes tochiach, הזאה hazaa for a person who's טמא, Tamei, that's what
you're doing הזאה hazaa for. שחל שביעי שלו להיות בשבת ובערב פסח,
Shechal shvi shelo lihyot be'Shabbat u've'erev Pesach, explicit, that שבת, Shabbat. ערב
פסח, Erev Pesach, all out, this guy's טמא tamei. מת, and the
only way he's going to bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. is
by doing the הזאה. hazaa, שהיא מצוה והיא משום שבות ואינה דוחה
את השבת. Shehi mitzvah v'hi mishum shvut v'eina docha et ha'Shabbat. So
obviously Rabbi Akiva had a tradition, which we find out now as
a tradition from Rabbi Eliezer, that you do not override הזאה hazaa,
for the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach?
even on שבת Shabbat, even if it's standing in the way of
bringing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. אלא ודאי הזאה דפסח אגמריה, Ella
vadai hazah d'Pesach agmrei, clearly the tradition that he was taught by
Rabbi Eliezer was הזאה hazaa, you do not do, even if it's
getting in the way. וכי מאחר דאגמריה, V'chi mei'achda d'agmrei, and since
that's what Rabbi Eliezer taught him, מאי טעמא קפרך ליה, mai ta'ama
kaparch leh, Rabbi Eliezer, why is Rabbi Eliezer sort of, you know,
challenging it, questioning it and saying, no, no, no, I think you
would do the הזאה? hazaa He taught Rabbi Akiva that you don't.
So the גמרא Gemara says, and this is what some of you
were referring to before, רבי אליעזר גמרא איתעקר ליה. Rabbi Eliezer gmara
itaker leh. We have this by an אמורא, Amora, we actually have
it by a תנא Tanna as well. Rabbi Eliezer forgot, you know,
he was old, he was sick, he forgot some of his learning.
ואתא רבי עקיבא לאדכוריה
גמריה. V'ata Rabbi Akiva l'azkurei gmareh. And Rabbi Akiva's coming to remind
him of his teaching. So therefore he reminds him by saying, you
know, by sort of hiding it. He's not saying, רבי, you forgot
what you said. But he said a statement which would make it
clear that he was taking the idea of not doing הזאה hazaa
as axiomatic. The same way you don't do הזאה, hazaa you shouldn't
do שחיטה. That's what you hear from that is, it's axiomatic you
don't do הזאה. hazaa. So the גמרא Gemara says ונימא ליה בהדיא,
v'neimah leh behedya, so just tell him, רבי, didn't you teach me
you're not allowed to do it on שבת? Shabbat. No, סבר לאו
אורח ארעא, savar lav orech ara, that it's not דרך ארץ Derech
Eretz to directly tell your teacher that he forgot. So you make
a statement that he'll remember, oh yeah, why is he saying that?
That's so weird. Oh yeah, maybe I did teach him that. Maybe
he heard that from me.
Doesn't Rabbi Akiva do this all the time?
Yeah, what can I tell you. Okay, so anyway, that's what the
גמרא Gemara says. I do want to say that it's interesting and
ironic that the same Rabbi Eliezer who we hear elsewhere never said
anything he didn't hear from his רבי, was all about the received
tradition and passing it on, we are finding out actually the worst
thing that can happen to somebody who's all about receiving the tradition
and passing it on is that you forget, right? And he דוקא
forgot and the way it was restored was through Rabbi Akiva, who
was much more about using your intellect and your logic, right? So
if you feel that you know your logic can get you to
the same place, you don't have to remember everything, you can figure
it out again. So I think there's something very, you know, beautiful,
ironic and beautiful about about about this little exchange. Yes?
Question. Back to Aaron's question, springing to
another. Can a טבול יום Tevul Yom eat תרומה? Terumah?
No. You have to wait until הערב שמש. He'erev Shemesh.
So I have to wait until after שבת?
Shabbat Oh, so your sense is that it won't even enable you
to do it this שבת Shabbat. if you do the הזאה. haza'ah,
Exactly.
And then you can do the separation of תרומה Terumah after שבת
Shabbat anyway.
That's an interesting question. Well, we're not separating it, we're eating it,
but you're not even eating it on שבת. Shabbat Yeah, so that's
a good point too. I mean, it's part of the same point
about דוחה, but you're sort of saying it's not even צרכי היום
Tzorchei HaYom because if you won't be able to eat until מוצאי
שבת. Motzaei Shabbat. Good question. Yeah, question, is this the same רבי
אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer, This רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrcanus who
is the בור סוד שאינו מאבד טיפה Bor Sud She'eino Me'abeid Tipah
and now he forgot?
Yeah, that's a very good point. Yeah, you're right. I think סתם
רבי
אליעזר,
Stam Rabbi
Eliezer, I think is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer Is סתם רבי אליעזר
Stam Rabbi Eliezer רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס? Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrcanus? I'm
trying to remember. That's an excellent point if it's true. Let me
find out. Hebrew Wikipedia is the answer to everything.
Although I don't know if I have Hebrew on this computer either.
I do.
And after I remember my Hebrew
keyboard. There are
several רבי
אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer.
for what's worth. Yeah, there are several. There
it is. Let's see. רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrcanus
and רבי אליעזר בן פדת. Rabbi Eliezer ben Pedat. Yeah, רבי אליעזר
בן הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Hyrcanus is סתם
רבי אליעזר.
Stam Rabbi
Eliezer. Right. And he's... right here in the second
line.
סתם רבי אליעזר Stam Rabbi Eliezer and
he's בור סוד שאינו מאבד טיפה. Bor Sud She'eino Me'abeid Tipah. So
according to this, eventually he was מאבד טיפה Me'abeid Tipah with his
again. So you're right, the בור סוד שאינו מאבד טיפה Bor Sud
She'eino Me'abeid Tipah is exactly because it's all about the מסורה Mesorah
and it means the tragedy of him actually forgetting is that much
greater. Yeah, thank you for making that connection. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues and says the following.
אמר... Okay, הזאה מאי טעמא לא דחיה שבת? Haza'ah Mai Ta'ama Lo
Dachya Shabbat? So what is, meaning not why does, why does קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach, not a justification? You know, that's just the question
of your position. Does קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. can it override even
the preparatory things you could have done beforehand? But on a general
שבת, Shabbat why can't you do הזאה? haza'ah, So the גמרא Gemara
says מכדי, Michti, טלטול בעלמא, Tiltul Be'alma, it's just moving stuff, you're
moving some water, why can't you do it?
תדחי שבת, Tidchi Shabbat, let it override שבת. Shabbat So the גמרא
Gemara says משום פסח, Mishum Pesach, certainly because of קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, what's the big dish, deal with doing הזאה haza'ah in general?
So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says גזירה שמא יטלנה
ויעבירנה ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים. Gezeirah Shema Yitlena Ve'yavirena Arba Amot Birshut
HaRabim. We're afraid that, you know, and this is רבא, Rava, רבא’s,
Rava you know, says this is the reason you don't blow שופר
on שבת Shabbos. and you don't take לולב Lulav on שבת. Shabbos
He’s all, he has a standard explanation in his back pocket that
the reason you don't do a number of things on שבת Shabbos.
is because you might come to carry. You know, the idea of
not doing תקיעת שופר Teki'at Shofar and not doing לולב Lulav on
שבת Shabbos is already in the משנה Mishna and it's not at
all clear that originally it was based on this concern of carrying,
but רבא Rava explains that it's based on carrying. Now, of course
it's interesting because the גמרא Gemara could have said that the reason
is like you don't go to the מקוה Mikvah on שבת Shabbos
in, except we, you know, we do in terms of, well, a
person does, but you don't let's say do a כלי Kli into
a מקוה Mikvah on שבת Shabbos because it looks like you're fixing
something. A person's allowed to go into מקוה Mikvah, because maybe you're
just going swimming. But the idea of that you're changing the status
of a vessel by putting into a מקוה, mikvah. you could have
said that the same is true here about the הזאה, haza'ah, you
know, you're changing the status of being טהור, Tahor,
and you know, what's the big deal? So maybe, you know, again,
maybe the הזאה haza'ah, just doesn't, it's not seen as transformative as
immersing something in a body of water. But it also could be
that we're looking for an explanation which would justify why, you know,
why such a strong דרבנן De'Rabanan that it would get in the
way of קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Maybe, maybe, you know, the opposing
positions might not say, I don't know, would רבי עקיבא say for
example you can't do מוקצה Muktzeh in order to bring the קרבן
פסח? Korban Pesach. I mean for God's sake, you can be עובר
Over on certain
דרבננס De'Rabanans even for somebody who's like a little bit of a
חולה Choleh or various types of issues, right? So maybe the גמרא's
Gemara question is not just why סתם Stam can you not do
הזאה, haza'ah, but what makes it such a דרבנן De'Rabanan that it's
getting that's so important, you know, and that raises an interesting question.
Could you be עובר Over on certain דרבננס for the sake? So
the גמרא Gemara makes the issue, the concern, it doesn't have to
be done anywhere. No, could be done anywhere, the הזאה. haza'ah, Then
the גמרא Gemara makes the concern that it could lead to חילול
שבת. Chilul Shabbat. But now the גמרא's Gemara got a question. How
would it lead to חילול שבת Chilul Shabbat according to רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer Even if you wound up carrying it in order to
do the הזאה, haza'ah that would be מותר Muttar because you're doing
it for bringing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach So the גמרא Gemara
says ולרבי אליעזר נעברי דאמר רבי אליעזר מכשירי מצוה דוחין את השבת.
U'LeRabbi Eliezer Ne'evrei, De'Amar Rabbi Eliezer Machshirei Mitzvah Dochin Et HaShabbat. So
how could רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. ever have said you can't do
הזאה, haza'ah right? That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. If for
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. you can do all these things for the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach. what makes for him, for other people we
know, any דרבנן D'Rabanan maybe, but for רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer what makes for him הזאה haza'ah? so important? And
the גמרא says, oh, because you might be עובר over a דאורייתא.
D'Oraisa. What big deal! You could do דאורייתא D'Oraisa for bringing the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So אמרי, Amri, no, but even preparatory
דאורייתא. D'Oraisas. So אמרי Amri הני מילי היכא דגברא גופיה חזי. hani
mili heicha de'gavra gufei chazi. And therefore, so you have to chop
firewood in order to make the knife, in order to do the
ברית מילה, Bris Milah, or if you have to go ahead and
carry the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach anything that's an obstacle, if you're
חייב chayav to bring it, it overrides שבת. Shabbos, But why would
he say הזאה haza'ah is different? Because הזאה, haza'ah? you're not in
the category of being obligated in a way. You're טמא. tamei, You're
not ראוי raui to bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach הכא גברא
גופיה לא חזי. hacha gavra gufei lo chazi. Your current status, although
it could be changed, but your current status is you're out of
the פרשה parsha of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach, So therefore, you're
not obligated right now. You could make yourself obligated by doing the
הזאה, haza'ah. but you're currently not obligated and therefore you don't override
שבת Shabbos. to make yourself obligated. So this is saying if it's
really true that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer taught רבי עקיבא, you don't
do הזאה, haza'ah, what makes הזאה haza'ah? different than everything else that
you can override if it's enabling, if it's getting in the way?
And it says because right now what makes הזאה haza'ah different is
right now you can't say that you have a חיוב. chiyuv. The
best you can say is I can do something to make myself
חייב, chayav, but you're not yet חייב, chayav, and therefore you do
not get the override. So לא רמי חיובא עליה, lo rami chiyuva
alei, the obligation is not on him. אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, so
now that's a very nice conceptual answer that even for רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer, there's a limit, not because הזאה haza'ah is more problematic,
but because your state is more problematic. So רבה Rabba says ולדברי
רבי אליעזר, v'divrei Rabbi Eliezer, according to this, let's draw out the
logical conclusions, making a distinction between being obligated with obstacles or not
being obligated. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer קטן ברי, katan
bari, if you have a healthy infant, eight days old, ברית מילה,
Bris Milah, you can מחממין לו חמין להברותו, mechaminin lo chamim lehavroso,
you can heat up hot water to get him stronger before the
ברית מילה, Bris Milah, if anyway the infant is able to have
a ברית מילה Bris Milah on his current state, ולמולו בשבת, u'lemolo
beShabbos, and to do a ברית מילה Bris Milah on שבת. Shabbos?
דחזי ליה קטן, de'chazi lei katan, because
the child is fit for it, he's חייב chayav to do a
ברית מילה, Bris Milah, and therefore these obstacles like, you know, are
overridden. קטן חולה, Katan choleh, but if the infant is sick and
in his current state you can't do the ברית מילה, Bris Milah,
אין מחממין לו חמין להברותו, ein mechaminin lo chamim lehavroso, but you
could go ahead and heat up some hot water and that process
would make him healthy and would make him fit for doing it,
you're not allowed to do it because that would be to not
have the obligation override the obstacles, but that would actually be to
do a transgression to make someone obligated, because right now you're not
obligated to do the ברית מילה Bris Milah on this קטן, katan,
and therefore you cannot do a violation in order to put him
into the category of obligation. דהא לא חזי ליה, de'ha lo chazi
lei, and right now he's not fit for it, right now he's
not obligated. So that's a very interesting application. אמר רבה, Amar Rabba,
רבה Rabba says back, ולברי הוא, v'labari hu, I don't get it,
in your first scenario, if the infant was such, was so healthy,
למה ליה חמין להברותו? lamah lei chamim lehavroso? Why are you heating
up the hot water if he's so healthy? Just for after? No,
it didn't say that. It said to get him ready for the
ברית מילה, Bris Milah, didn't say for after. אלא אמר רבה, Ela
amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba says הכל חולים הם אצל מילה, akol
cholim heim etzel milah, so all are considered sick for the ברית
מילה, Bris Milah, meaning even healthy babies needed, you know, are needed
to have hot water heated for them, even they are not really
fit for the ברית מילה Bris Milah until you get them ready
for it, until you, you know, have them have, put them in
the hot water. What? מקדים רפואה למכה. makdim refuah lemakah. אחד קטן
ברי ואחד חולה, echad katan bari v'echad choleh, אין מחממין לו חמין
להברותו ולמולו בשבת. ein mechaminin lo chamim lehavroso u'lemolo beShabbos. Now that's
interesting. You would have said oh, he says it's universal, you can
always do it. No,
universally you can never do it, once we think that according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you can't do something if somebody is not
yet obligated. So he says really before any, even a healthy infant
has been prepared for it, you cannot do the ברית מילה. Bris
Milah. How do
you do ברית מילה Bris Milah on שבת Shabbos, then, according to
him? You heat up the hot water from beforehand. Stay hot. Yeah,
you put it, you keep it on the fire. Okay, but he
said if it's really true that you need to do it in
order for him to sustain the ברית מילה Bris Milah even if
he's healthy, then he's right now without it being done, not yet
fit, and you can't override שבת Shabbos. according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer Okay, this is even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, is more lenient.
Let's not forget that the חכמים Chachamim never let you do anything
on שבת you could have done the day before. דהא לא חזי,
de'ha lo chazi, and right now in that state even a healthy
baby isn't fit. Okay, so that's a very fascinating distinct limit within
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Yes you can override דאורייתא, D'Oraisa, דרבנן in
order to do a ברית מילה, Bris Milah, in order to do
פסח, Pesach, even preparatory things once you're obligated, but you can't override
things to put yourself in a state of obligation, which would be
the story about the guy who's waiting for the הזאה. haza'ah on
the seventh day. So it's not about the הזאה, it's about his
status. So now the גמרא says like this: איתיביה אביי, Aysvei Abaye,
אביי Abaye asks on this, ערל שלא מל אינו כרת, arel she'lo
mal eino kares, even רבי אליעזר. רבי אליעזר says that if somebody
has a is uncircumcised and he could be circumcised, it's not like
it's a סכנה sakanah for him, he could get circumcised and he
didn't, he gets כרת kares because he could have brought the קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach today, ערב פסח, Pesach. he could have found a
מוהל, mohel, done the ברית מילה Brit Milah and brought his קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach So he's not טמא, tamei he's not היה בדרך
רחוקה hayah b'derech rechokah and he's in a position where he could
have he could have brought it. So the fact that he allowed
himself to remain in that position is not doesn't get him off.
And for שבת, do you do ברית מילה Brit Milah then?
No, not on well that would be a related question, but we're
not even talking about שבת. So now the גמרא is going to
ask him a very good a very good question based on this.
You can only be חייב כרת chayav kares if you're חייב chayav
to bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach But if רבי אליעזר thinks
that a טמא tamei person isn't in the category yet of being
חייב, chayav, then of the ערל, arel, even though he could have
a ברית מילה, Brit Milah, it's like the טמא tamei person who
could do the הזאה, but right now you're not חייב, chayav, so
how could you be חייב כרת? chayav kares? So the גמרא says,
דהא הכא דגופיה לא חזי, de'ha hacha de'gufeh lo chazi, the person
himself is not fit, וקתני ענוש כרת, v'ka-tani anush kares, you get
כרת, kares, אלמא רמי חיובא עליה, alma rami chiyuva alei, you see
that he has an obligation even though he right now is not
fit because it's something that can be fixed. So טומאה tumah also
is something that can be fixed. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so said
רבא, Rava, קסבר רבי אליעזר, Kasavar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר is of
the position, אין שוחטין וזורקין על טמאי שרץ, ein shochtin v'zorkin al
t'mei sheretz, that somebody who is טמא tamei. for touching a dead
rodent, now is you don't you can't set the קרבן פסח korban
Pesach? even though he'll be טהור tahor that night until this guy
has gone to the מקוה. mikvah, I touched a dead rodent, right
now I am טמא. tamei If I go to the מקוה, mikvah,
I'll finish being טהור tahor tonight, but I've gone to the מקוה,
mikvah I'm not really considered טמא tamei. now and you can bring
you can bring my קרבן פסח korban Pesach for me. But if
I've yet to go to the מקוה mikvah and you bring the
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach even if I go to the מקוה mikvah,
afterwards, your bringing up of the קרבן פסח korban Pesach for me
right now doesn't count because right now I am טמא. tamei, Basically
what רבא Rava is going to say is that טומאה tumah is
different. טומאה tumah we'll see why, but he'll say if you're טמא,
tamei, you're considered out of the category, out of the obligation. If
you're an ערל, arel, you're in the obligation with an obstacle. That's
basically the difference we're looking for, here he's going to try to
argue why. So number one, a guy who is טמא, tamei, even
if he could go to the מקוה, mikvah which is similar to
a guy who is waiting for הזאה because he could have הזאה,
right now you can't bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach for me.
וכל מילתא דאיתא בציבור, v'chol milsa d'isa b'tzibur, anybody for whom in
this status you would be pushed off, you'd bring a
פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, בציבור עבדי בטומאה, b'tzibur avdi b'tumah, if it
was true about the majority of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, they would
do it. So even if the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
could go to the מקוה mikvah today, right now on ערב פסח,
Pesach. but if right now they're all טמא, tamei, then then even
without going to the מקוה mikvah they could do it because it's
the principle of טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra b'tzibur.
But it doesn't apply to טמאי שרץ. t'mei sheretz.
Oh, טמאי שרץ, t'mei sheretz, they couldn't be... no, it doesn't apply
to זבים zavim and things that are worse. It applies to things
that are lighter,
according to this it applies to things that are lighter. The only
reason שרץ sheretz would be different is because you go to the
מקוה mikvah today and you're saying that doesn't matter. וכל מילתא דאיתא
בציבור, v'chol milsa d'isa b'tzibur, anything that would be done overridden in
the ציבור, tzibur, so basically the argument is if the ציבור tzibur
is טמא, tamei, even if they could go to the מקוה today,
they it's still say טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra b'tzibur. And once
that's true, איתא ביחיד, isa b'yachid, then anything that's done with the
ציבור tzibur is done by the יחיד, yachid, וכל מילתא דליתא בציבור
ליתא ביחיד. v'chol milsa d'leisa b'tzibur leisa b'yachid. And anything that's not
with the ציבור tzibur doesn't apply to them, doesn't apply. What does
this mean? We'll be do it a bit more clearly. ערלה, Arlah,
so the issue of circum- of a foreskin, non-circumcised, דכולי
ציבור ערלים, de'kulei tzibur arelim, if you have the majority that is
an ערל, arel, מי אמרינן להו קומו מהול, mi amrinan lehu kumu
mehul, we never have an idea, here's the key difference. We never
have an idea of ערלה הותרה בציבור, arlah hutra b'tzibur, right? The
idea is טומאה הותרה בציבור. tumah hutra b'tzibur. So if we had
the whole ציבור tzibur of men was ערלים, arelim, like the story
by יהושע, Yehoshua, right? We would say go do a מילה, milah,
we wouldn't say do it בערלה. b'arlah. We don't have that principle.
קומו מהול נפשייכו, Kumu mehul nafshaychu, and they'd
have and they'd bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach and they wouldn't
be it wouldn't override. יחיד נמי אמרינן ליה קום מהול. Yachid nami
amrinan leh kum mahul. So if a יחיד yachid is an ערל,
arel, the same way we tell a ציבור tzibur we don't say
הותרה, hutra, we say דחיה, d'chayah, go do the ברית מילה. Brit
Milah. To a יחיד yachid as well we would say דחיה, d'chayah,
go do the ברית מילה. Brit Milah. ועביד פסחא, v'avid pischa, and
do the פסח. Pesach ואי לא מהיל ועביד, v'ei lo mahil v'avid,
and if you don't do the מילה milah and you do, ענוש
כרת, anush kares, you get כרת. kares. טומאה, Tumah, now, so basically
the point is why by the guy who has an ערל arel
do we say you're obligated and we see the ערלות arlus as
an obstacle? Because by the
ציבור tzibur we would insist that they get a ברית מילה. Brit
Milah. We wouldn't say do it בערלה. b'arlah. So the basic way
we approach ערלה arlah is, deal with the problem, you're obligated, deal
with the problem.
Even if it be on שבת?
Well, that might be then and then even if it would be
on שבת, right, according to רבי אליעזר, even if it be on
שבת. Now, טומאה, tumah, where were we, דאי כולי ציבור טמאים נינהו,
de'i kulei tzibur t'meim ninhu, by טומאה tumah if the majority was
טמאים, t'meim, לא. לא מהדרינן עליה, lo mahadrinan alei, we wouldn't do
the הזאה, אלא עבדינן בטומאה. ella avdinan be'tumah. We would say, you're
טמא, tamei, fine, we're not going to insist you do הזאה, we'll
let you do it בטומאה. be'tumah. So if the ציבור tzibur was
טמא, tamei we wouldn't insist that they become טהור. tahor. So if
we're not going to insist that the ציבור tzibur becomes טהור, tahor,
so יחיד נמי פטור, yachid nami patur, we're not going to insist
that the יחיד yachid becomes טהור. tahor. So it's a little complicated,
but the basic argument is, it's clear that רבי אליעזר sees the
ערל arel as obligated and if he doesn't deal with it, he's
חייב כרת. chayav kares. So how could you say the טמא tamei.
is not obligated and he doesn't have a license to override? And
the answer is because טומאה tumah is different. We have a principle
of טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra be'tzibur and therefore our approach to
the ציבור tzibur would be we wouldn't insist that they be מטהר
metaher themselves, we'd allow them to stay טמא. tamei So somewhat ironically,
we allow the יחיד yachid to stay טמא tamei and therefore we
say, you're not obligated. Do פסח שני, Pesach Sheini, but you're not
obligated. And therefore we do not override because we don't insist that
he become טהור. tahor. Let's just finish a little bit more because
I've got to just get
through. אמר ליה רב פפא בריה דרב יהושע לרבא, Amar lei Rav
Pappa berei de'Rav Yehoshua le'Rava, בפרה ופסח שני, הוי פסח שני דליתא
בציבור ואיתא ביחיד, be'parah u'Pesach Sheini, havei Pesach Sheini de'leisa be'tzibur ve'isa
be'yachid, that the ציבור tzibur doesn't bring a פסח שני Pesach Sheini
and a יחיד yachid does, so we can't have something we sort
of obligate a יחיד yachid to do that we don't obligate the
ציבור tzibur to do. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so this comparison
doesn't work. אמר ליה, no, שאני התם דהוי ליה ציבור בראשון. shani
hasam de'havei lei tzibur be'rishon. They're not doing פסח שני Pesach Sheini
because the ציבור tzibur will always wind up doing the first פסח.
So anyway, my comparison still holds. So anyway, it's a little complicated,
but I want to just get to the fact that the גמרא
rejects it. So we can end with some more something a little
bit clearer. מיתיבי. Meisivei. יכול לא יהא אנוש כרת אלא שהיה טהור
ושלא היה בדרך רחוקה. Yachol lo yei'einosh kares ella she'hayah tahor ve'she'lo
hayah be'derech rechokah. I might think only one gets כרת kares if
somebody that was טהור tahor and was not far away. ערל וטמא
שרץ ושאר כל הטמאים מניין? Arel u'tmei sheretz u'shear kol hatmei'im minayin?
How do you know if somebody had a problem, but a problem
that could have been addressed, like he was an ערל, arel, but
could have had a ברית מילה bris milah today, or he had
טמא שרץ, tmei sheretz, and he could have jumped into the מקווה
mikvah today. How do you know that even though they are in
that state, they're still חייב chayav for not bringing קרבן פסח? korban
Pesach Okay, good point, right? They are right now not in a
fit state, but they could be. תלמוד לומר והאיש, Talmud lomar ve'ha'ish,
and the person, which means even other cases, even cases like this.
So what do you see? You see both an ערל arel and
somebody that's טמא tamei, just for one day are considered obligated and
have to fix their status. למימרא דמהדר
אטמא שרץ, Leimira de'mahader a'tmei sheretz, since we're dealing with the case
of טמא שרץ, tmei sheretz, קסבר אין שוחטין וזורקין על טמא שרץ.
kasavar ein shochtin ve'zorkin al tmei sheretz. Clearly it's, the point is
that right now you can't bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach like
the ערל. arel. דאי שוחטין וזורקין על טמא שרץ, De'i shochtin ve'zorkin
al tmei sheretz, if you could have the פסח brought for you
in this status, למה לי לאהדורי עליה? lamah li le'ahadurei alei? It
wouldn't have been a special case. היינו טהור. Hainu tahor. It's just
like you're טהור, tahor, you know? Obviously, what this ברייתא braisa is
looking for is how do you know somebody that even though right
now they can't bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach, because they're ערל,
arel, because they're טמא, tamei that nevertheless if they can fix it,
they're obligated? So clearly we're assuming that this טומאה tumah is something
that's an obstacle. אלמא אף על גב דלא חזי, Alma af al
gav de'lo chazi, you see even though it's not fit, חיובא רמיא
עליה, chiyuva ramya alei, he has the obligation. ואף על גב דליתא
בציבור איתא ביחיד, Ve'af al gav de'leisa be'tzibur isa be'yachid, even though
the ציבור tzibur would not have this obligation, could do it בטומאה,
be'tumah, he has an obligation to fix it. So basically it's a
ברייתא braisa that makes it clear that somebody who is טמא tamei,
like an ערל arel is considered obligated and has to fix it.
So we're back to our question, why do you not do הזאה,
what makes טומאה tumah different?
וכולהו ציבור טמאי שרץ, Ve'kuleihu tzibur tmei sheretz, and you think the
whole ציבור tzibur is טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, then
they would bring it בטומאה? be'tumah? Yes. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar
Rava, רבא Rava says, קסבר רבי אליעזר שוחטין וזורקין על טמא שרץ.
kasavar Rabbi Eliezer shochtin ve'zorkin al tmei sheretz. Fine, here's what רבי
אליעזר says. The reason is the opposite of what we were saying.
It's not that you're so out of the category we don't allow
it; you're already in the category, so we don't allow it. Even
though you're טמא, tamei, you can go ahead and have a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach, brought for you. והוא הדין לטמא מת בשביעי שלו.
Ve'hu hadin le'tmei meis be'shivii shelo. So this is the exact opposite.
It's not you're so out of the category, you're already able, your
group can bring a קרבן פסח for you even though you haven't
had the הזאה yet. So why would you need somebody to do
הזאה if your group can already bring the קרבן פסח for you
already in this state? Can you think why you still want to
be טהור? tahor?
You still need to eat it!
You need to eat the קרבן that night. So הזאה למה? haza'ah
lamah? Why do you need the הזאה? לאכילה. La'achilah. So the קרבן
פסח right now can be brought for you. The only reason you
need the הזאה is so that you could eat it. So you
know what? אכילת פסחים לא מעכבא. Achilas pesachim lo me'akva. Opposite, I
knew you'd enjoy that, opposite to what we've been saying since day
one. He's saying that you don't have to eat the קרבן פסח
to be יוצא. yotzei. Now תוספות Tosafos says that only in a
case like this where the reason you can't eat it is that
you're טמא, tamei, okay, not סתם, stam, but nevertheless, that's the argument.
So basically the גמרא's answer, I want to just read, I know
we're over but two more lines to get the ודא v'da answer
is why for רבי אליעזר if you can do everything is the
one thing you can't do הזאה? And the answer is because you're
already so much in the category you'll be יוצא yotzei without the
הזאה. אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא. Amar lei Rav Adda
bar Ahava le'Rava. If you can't, if you can't eat, if you
don't do the הזאה, then it's being שחט-ed for שלא לאוכליו, shelo
le-ochlav, somebody who can't eat
it. So אמר ליה, שלא לאוכליו בחולה וזקן דלא חזי. shelo le-ochlav
be-choleh ve-zaken delo chazi. No, that's somebody who's never able to eat
it, like a חולה choleh or זקן, zaken, although we would think
that's more circumstantial. אבל האי, aval hai, this guy who's טמא, tamei
מחזי חזי, mechazi chazi, he's fit. תיקוני הוא דלא מתקן, tikunei hu
delo metaken, he's just not doing what it needs in order to
enable him to eat. But since in theory he could make himself
fit, he's considered a theoretical אוכל. ochal. So the גמרא here basically
goes against everything that we've been saying. There are cases where you
don't have to eat the קרבן פסח, even somebody who can't eat,
it's not שלא לאוכליו shelo le-ochlav since in theory he's a טמא
but he could fix it. Similarly, you wonder if he was an
ערל. arel. An ערל arel would have to be שלא לאוכליו shelo
le-ochlav since in theory he could get a ברית מילה. bris milah.
So all of a sudden the category of שלא לאוכליו shelo le-ochlav
is different. And the whole point of this is to say why
according to רבי אליעזר, if you can do everything to bring the
קרבן פסח, can you not do הזאה? And rather than the first
answer, which is 'cause you're already, you're completely out of the category,
here it's the opposite. You're so in the category that even without
the הזאה you'll be יוצא, yotzei, and therefore since even without the
הזאה you'll be יוצא, yotzei, we do not allow you to do
the הזאה even according to רבי אליעזר.